<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>lett 4 Marie to Ortenisa Stella</title>
                <author key="mancini-marie">Marie Mancini</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcribed and tanslated by</resp>
                    <name xml:id="smn">Sarah M. Nelson</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Edited by</resp>
                    <name xml:id="am">Alessandro Martina</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoded by</resp>
                    <name xml:id="lrm">Liam R. Marchant</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>The Correspondence of Marie Mancini</authority>
                <publisher>University of Idaho Library</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>https://thecdil.github.io/mancini_source/</addrLine>
                </address>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Inquiry and Learning</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Room 211</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Idaho Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Moscow, ID 83844-2350</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>https://cdil.lib.uidaho.edu/</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2020</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>The Correspondence of Marie Mancini is freely distributed by the Center for Digital Inquiry and Learning at the University of Idaho Library and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-ND 4.0) United States License.
                    </p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Correspondence of Marie Mancini</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title key="1672_07_14_mm2os" type="letter" n="04">lett 4 Marie to Ortenisa Stella</title>
                    <author key="mancini-marie">Marie Mancini</author>
                    <persName type="addressee" key="ortensia-stella">Ortensia Stella</persName>
                    <date when="1672-07-14">July 14 1672</date>
                </bibl>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository key="colonna-archive">
                            Colonna Archive, library of the abbey of Santa Scolastica, Subiaco, Italy
                        </repository>
                        <collection>
                            Lettere di Maria Mancini
                        </collection>
                        <idno type="collection">IICP1</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <p>Document is one leaf, handwritten on recto and verso.</p>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <extent>
                                    <measure type="composition" unit="leaf" quantity="1">1 leaf</measure>
                                </extent>
                            </supportDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc hands="1">
                            <handNote xml:id="mancini-marie" medium="black">
                                Marie Mancini handwritten
                            </handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origDate when="1672-07-14">July 14 1672</origDate>
                            <origPlace>
                                <placeName key="grenoble">Grenoble</placeName>
                            </origPlace>
                        </origin>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>
                        The archive incorrectly labels this letter with date 1672-07-01. The correct date is 1672-07-14.
                    </p>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2020-05-26" who="#lrm">
                Initial creation of XML from non-XML electronic files
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="letter" xml:id="letter_1672_07_14_mm2os_raw" n="04" facs="DSCF8221">
                <head type="raw" xml:lang="fr" />
                <note resp="#smn" xml:id="archive-note">
                Collocazione II-C.P.1. lett. 4
                Lettere di Maria Mancini – 1672
                Numero d'ordine – 4

                Donna Maria Mancini-Colonna

                =

                Lettera alla Contessa Ortensia Stella
                in data	1&#xb0; [[? it looks like a "14" on the letter]] Luglio 1672 da Grenoble
                Sigillo mancante – tutta di pugno –
                oggetto:
                </note>
                <pb facs="DSCF8222"/>
                <note resp="#smn">
                [[This letter is written by a hand other than Marie’s. This writer often leaves spaces after "a" that make it look like 2 separate words, but I have transcribed here without the spaces. For example, "avoit" looks like "a voit" … "avais" looks like "a vais" … etc.]]
                </note>
                <note resp="#smn">
                [[This letter seems to be a recopied, more legible version of the letter written by Marie, which appears on images DSCF8231-DSCF8232.]]
                </note>
                <note resp="#smn">
                [[On the right half of the sheet:]]
                </note>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName key="grenoble">a grenoble</placeName>
                        <date when="1672-07-14">ce 14<hi rend="superscript">me</hi>[[iullect?]]</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>ma pauvre contesse ie vous aye touiours aimee et vous aymer&#233; cest pour n&#233; vous faire pas d'affaire que jay manqu&#233; de confiance non que ie doutasse de vous sachant fort bien a quelle point vous este segrette si on avoit montre les lettres que iavais lesse vous oriez veu que ie ne vous avais pas [["oubli" crossed out]] oublie <hi rend="superscript">et</hi> dans les partages vous auriez reconu mon amitie—ausi bien que les autre mais lon [[something crossed out]] hut trop de crinte ce qui fit d&#233;chirer les lettre a [[it looks like "a" is written over "et"]] ce luy qui en estoit charge mais vous poures dire a marquatelli quil vous donne le revenu de mille escus de' l'argant que jay nelle</p>
                <pb facs="DSCF8223"/>
                <note resp="#smn">[[On the left half of the sheet:]]</note>
                <p>comunita en attandant quil vous puisse donner la somme Monsieur de moriez est charge de tout le reste pour arnolfiny Madame diodaty, et les austres celles qui oront de l'amitie pour moy de mes femmes me viendrons trouver trouver mais [["nanet" crossed out]] nanet est trop angagee et [["cons" crossed out]] constance pour tiche elle a gran tort de nestre pas venue [[avec?]] fanchon elle est a moy et ie sere bien [[aize? / aise?]] de [[la voir? / lavoir?]] ne voulant pas de visages nouveaus jay ordonn&#233; aussi a antoine et anna quelque chosse chacune [["cha" is written over "elle"]] elle mont fort bien servie anvoyez moy nene et vous me feres un gran plaisir faite moy venir de mes filles celle qui</p>
                <note resp="#smn">[[On the right half of the sheet:]]</note>
                <p>serons bien [[aize? / aise?]] de mevenir trouver si lon leurs vouloit permettre de me porter ausi quelque ardes ianne grand besoin et faite que marquatelli retire les bimestres des monts et me les faire tenir vous poures faire mes afaires astheur a rome ie sere ancor icy lontenps iattand mon frere Mad.<hi rend="superscript">a</hi> mazarin est an savoye ie suis fort soli[[letters crossed out]]terre et tout a vous</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>contessa</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter" xml:id="letter_1672_07_14_mm2os_edit" n="04" facs="DSCF8221">
                <head type="edit" xml:lang="fr" />
                <pb facs="DSCF8222"/>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName key="grenoble">&#xc0; Grenoble</placeName>
                        <date when="1672-07-14">ce 14<hi rend="superscript">me</hi> juillet</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Ma pauvre comtesse, je vous ai toujours aim&#233;e et vous aimerai toujours. C'est pour ne pas vous faire d'affaire que j'ai manqu&#233; de confiance, non que je doutasse de vous, sachant fort bien &#224; quel point vous &#234;tes secr&#232;te. Si on avait montr&#233; les lettres que j'avais laiss&#233;es, vous auriez vu que je ne vous avais pas oubli&#233;e et dans les partages, vous auriez reconnu mon amiti&#233;—aussi bien que les autres. Mais l'on eut trop de crainte, ce qui fit d&#233;chirer les lettres &#224; celui qui en &#233;tait charg&#233;. Mais vous pourrez dire &#224; Marcatelli qu'il vous donne le revenu de mille &#233;cus de l’argent que j'ai dans les</p>
                <pb facs="DSCF8223"/>
                <p>communaut&#233;s, en attendant qu'il puisse vous donner la somme. Monsieur de Mori&#232;s est charg&#233; de tout le reste pour Arnolfini, Madame Diodati et les autres. Celles de mes femmes qui auront de l'amiti&#233; pour moi viendront me trouver, mais Nanette est trop engag&#233;e et Constance. Pour Tiche, elle a grand tort de n'&#234;tre pas venue avec Fanchon. Elle est &#224; moi et je [[serai / serais]] bien aise de l'avoir, ne voulant pas de visages nouveaux. J'ai ordonn&#233; aussi &#224; Antonia et Anna quelque chose chacune ; elle m'ont fort bien servie. Envoyez-moi N&#233;n&#233; et vous me ferez un grand plaisir. Faites-moi venir de mes filles celles qui seront bien aise de venir me trouver. Si l'on voulait leur permettre de me porter aussi quelques hardes, j'en ai grand besoin. Et faites que Marcatelli retire les bimestres des monts et qu'il me les fasse tenir. Vous pourrez faire mes affaires &#224; cette heure &#224; Rome. Je serai encore longtemps ici ; j'attends mon fr&#232;re. Madame Mazarin est en Savoie.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>Je suis fort solitaire et tout &#224; vous,</salute>
                    <signed>Contessa</signed>.
                </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter" xml:id="letter_1672_07_14_mm2os_translation" n="04" facs="DSCF8221">
                <head type="translation" xml:lang="en" />
                <pb facs="DSCF8222"/>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName key="grenoble">Grenoble</placeName>
                        <date when="1672-07-14">14 July</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>My poor <persName key="ortensia-stella">Countess</persName>, I have always loved you, and I always will. It was to avoid causing trouble for you that I showed a lack of confidence, not because I doubted you, knowing full well how discreet you are. If you'd been shown the letters that I left, you would have seen that I had not forgotten you, and in the division of goods, you would have recognized my friendship—as the others would have as well. But people were too fearful, which caused the letters to be ripped up by the man who had charge of them. But you can tell <persName key="marcatelli" type="annotate" xml:id="a1672-07-14" n="1">Marcatelli</persName> that he should give you the revenue of a thousand &#233;cus from the money that I have in the</p>
                <pb facs="DSCF8223"/>
                <p><ref type="annotate" xml:id="b1672-07-14" n="2">communities</ref>, until such time as he can give you the full amount. <persName key="mories" type="annotate" xml:id="c1672-07-14" n="3">Monsieur de Mori&#232;s</persName> is responsible for all the rest for <persName key="arnolfini">Arnolfini</persName>, <persName key="mme-diodati">Madame Diodati</persName>, and the <ref type="annotate" xml:id="d1672-07-14" n="4">others</ref>. Those of my women who feel kindly toward me will come to join me, but <persName key="nanette">Nanette</persName> is overburdened and <persName key="constance">Constance</persName>. As for <persName key="tiche">Tiche</persName>, she was very wrong not to have come with <persName key="fanchon" type="annotate" xml:id="e1672-07-14" n="5">Fanchon</persName>. She is in my service, and I [[will be / would be]] glad to have her, since I don’t want new faces. I have also sent orders to <persName key="antonia">Antonia</persName> and to <persName key="anna">Anna</persName>; they have served me very well. Send me <persName key="nene" type="annotate" xml:id="f1672-07-14" n="6">N&#233;n&#233;</persName>, and you’ll please me greatly. Have those of my maids come who are pleased to join me. If they were permitted to bring me some old clothes, too, I have great need of them. And have <persName key="marcatelli">Marcatelli</persName> withdraw the bimonthly revenue from the mountains and send it to me. You may attend to my affairs now in <placeName key="rome">Rome</placeName>. I will be here for a long time yet; I’m waiting for my brother. <persName key="mme-mazarin">Madame Mazarin</persName> is in <placeName key="savoy">Savoy</placeName>.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>I am very lonely and entirely yours,</salute>
                    <signed>
                        <persName key="marie-mancini">Contessa</persName>.
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
