<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>lett 14 Marie to Ortenisa Stella</title>
                <author key="mancini-marie">Marie Mancini</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcribed and translated by</resp>
                    <name xml:id="smn">Sarah M. Nelson</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Edited by</resp>
                    <name xml:id="am">Alessandro Martina</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoded by</resp>
                    <name xml:id="lrm">Liam R. Marchant</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>The Correspondence of Marie Mancini</authority>
                <publisher>University of Idaho Library</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>https://thecdil.github.io/mancini_source/</addrLine>
                </address>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Inquiry and Learning</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Room 211</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Idaho Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Moscow, ID 83844-2350</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>https://cdil.lib.uidaho.edu/</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2020</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>The Correspondence of Marie Mancini is freely distributed by the Center for Digital Inquiry and Learning at the University of Idaho Library and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-ND 4.0) United States License.
                    </p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Correspondence of Marie Mancini</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title key="1672_12_02_mm2lc" type="letter" n="14">lett 14 Marie to Lorenzo</title>
                    <author key="mancini-marie">Marie Mancini</author>
                    <persName type="addressee" key="colonna-lorenzo">Lorenzo Colonna</persName>
                    <date when="1672-12-02">December 2 1672</date>
                </bibl>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository key="colonna-archive">
                            Colonna Archive, library of the abbey of Santa Scolastica, Subiaco, Italy
                        </repository>
                        <collection>
                            Lettere di Maria Mancini
                        </collection>
                        <idno type="collection">IICP1</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <p>Document is one leaf, handwritten on recto and verso.</p>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <extent>
                                    <measure type="composition" unit="leaf" quantity="1">1 leaf</measure>
                                </extent>
                            </supportDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc hands="1">
                            <handNote xml:id="mancini-marie" medium="black">
                                Marie Mancini handwritten
                            </handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origDate when="1672-12-02">December 2 1672</origDate>
                            <origPlace>
                                <placeName key="avenay">Avenay</placeName>
                            </origPlace>
                        </origin>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation>
                    <p></p>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2020-05-29" who="#lrm">
                Initial creation of XML from non-XML electronic files
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="letter" xml:id="letter_1672_12_02_mm2lc_raw" n="14" facs="DSCF8488">
                <head type="raw" xml:lang="it" />
                <note resp="#smn" xml:id="archive-note">
                Collocazione -II-C.P.1. lettera 14
                Lettere di Maria Mancini – 1672
                Numero d'ordine – 14

                D. Maria Colonna-Mancini –

                =

                Lettera al Contestabile Colonna
                in data	2 Dicembre 1672 d’Avenay
                Sigillo – tutta di pugno –

                oggetto:
                </note>
                <pb facs="DSCF8489"/>
                <note resp="#smn">
                [[On the left side of the image, the diagonally folded paper with address written on outside: 
                "A Monsieur
                Monsieur le Conestable 
                Colonna
                Roma"
                + 1 red wax seal]]
                </note>
                <note resp="#smn">
                [[Along the bottom edge of the left side of the paper, parallel with the edge and upside down, appears to be written the date—probably written by an archivist or a secretary? The ink looks similar to Marie's ink.]]    
                </note>
                <note resp="#smn">
                [[On the right half of the sheet:]]   
                </note>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName key="avenay">D'avenay</placeName>
                        <date when="1672-12-02">ce 2<hi rend="superscript">me</hi> decem[[bre]] 1672</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>L'a vostra letra del primo di novembre ma aportata molta consolatione per scorger in essa sempre piu il vostro affetto al quale io corispondero comforme Al obligo mio et al merito vostro. espetto [[Marie appears to have written an "e" over the "a" of "aspetto"]] di giorno in giorno mio fratello; il quale mi scriveno abbi obtenuto di condurmi seco a lione, non credo pero di esseguir [[something crossed out]] la sua intentione; non trovandomi in stato dintraprender tal viaggio in questa staggione; sono tuttavia nella badia d'avenay molto solitaria non avendo altra satisfactione che di studiar con Mr boniel; mio cappellano; il quale possede bene la lingua francese latina e italiana et spagnola. il mio principale</p>
                <pb facs="DSCF8490"/>
                <note resp="#smn">
                [[on the right half of the sheet:]]   
                </note>
                <p>studio pero sara di non far cosa alcuna di cui voi ne il mondo possa trovar a redire ne far torto a miei figli quali amo teneramente; &#233; spero cola gratia di dio farvi conoscere che sono veramente <hi rend="superscript">&#233; come bramate</hi> vostra</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed><persName key="mancini-marie">M.M.C.</persName></signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter" xml:id="letter_1672_12_02_mm2lc_edit" n="14" facs="DSCF8488">
                <head type="edit" xml:lang="fr" />
                <pb facs="DSCF8489"/>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName key="gavenay">D'Avenay</placeName>
                        <date when="1672-12-02">ce 2 décembre 1672</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>La vostra lettera del primo di novembre mi ha apportata molta consolazione per scorgere in essa sempre pi&#249; il vostro affetto al quale io corrisponder&#242; conforme all'obbligo mio ed al merito vostro. Aspetto di giorno in giorno mio fratello, il quale mi scriveva di aver ottenuto di condurmi seco a Lione. Non credo per&#242; di eseguire la sua intenzione, non trovandomi in stato di intraprendere un tal viaggio in questa stagione. Sono tuttavia nella bad&#236;a di Avenay, molto solitaria, non avendo altra soddisfazione che di studiare con monsieur Boniel, mio cappellano, il quale possiede bene la lingua francese, latina, italiana e spagnola. Il mio principale</p>
                <pb facs="DSCF8490"/>
                <p>studio per&#242; sar&#224; di non fare cosa alcuna su cui voi n&#233; il mondo possa trovare da ridire, n&#233; fare torto a miei figli, i quali amo teneramente. E spero colla grazia di Dio farvi conoscere che sono veramente, e come bramate, vostra.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed rend="ti-1"><persName key="mancini-marie">M. M. C.</persName></signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter" xml:id="letter_1672_12_02_mm2lc_translation" n="14" facs="DSCF8488">
                <head type="translation" xml:lang="en" />
                <pb facs="DSCF8489"/>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName key="avenay" type="annotate" xml:id="a1672_12_02_mm2lc" n="1">Avenay</placeName>,
                        <date when="1672-12-02">2 December 1672</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Your letter of the first of November was a great consolation to me, as I was ever more able to discern in it your affection, which I will return, in keeping with my obligation and your merit. I am expecting my brother from one day to the next; he wrote me that he had obtained permission to take me with him to <placeName key="lyon">Lyon</placeName>. I don’t think, though, that I will go along with his plan, as I don't feel in condition to undertake such a journey in this season. And yet, I am very lonely in the <placeName key="avenay">Avenay</placeName> abbey, having no other satisfaction than to study with <persName key="boniel">Monsieur Boniel</persName>, my chaplain, who has a good command of French, Latin, Italian, and <ref type="annotate" xml:id="b1672_12_02_mm2lc" n="2">Spanish</ref>. My chief</p>
                <pb facs="DSCF8490"/>
                <p>concern, however, will be to do nothing with which either you or society could find fault, and to cause no harm to my sons, whom I love tenderly. And I hope, with the grace of God, to show you that I am truly, as you yearn for me to be, yours.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed rend="ti-1">
                        <persName key="marie-mancini">M. M. C.</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
