<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>lett 12 Marie to Lorenzo</title>
                <author key="mancini-marie">Marie Mancini</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcribed and translated by</resp>
                    <name xml:id="smn">Sarah M. Nelson</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Edited by</resp>
                    <name xml:id="am">Alessandro Martina</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoded by</resp>
                    <name xml:id="lrm">Liam R. Marchant</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoded by</resp>
                    <name xml:id="kx">Klytie Xu</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>The Correspondence of Marie Mancini</authority>
                <publisher>University of Idaho Library</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>https://thecdil.github.io/mancini_source/</addrLine>
                </address>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Inquiry and Learning</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Room 211</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Idaho Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Moscow, ID 83844-2350</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>https://cdil.lib.uidaho.edu/</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2022</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>The Correspondence of Marie Mancini is freely distributed by the Center for Digital Inquiry and Learning at the University of Idaho Library and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-ND 4.0) United States License.
                    </p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note>Marie Mancini writes to Lorenzo Colonna about rumors and the aftermath of her running away. Marie also asks for Lorenzo's trust.</note>
            </notesStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Correspondence of Marie Mancini</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title key="1672_09_27_mm2lc" type="letter" n="12">lett 12 Marie to Lorenzo</title>
                    <author key="mancini-marie">Marie Mancini</author>
                    <persName type="addressee" key="colonna-lorenzo">Lorenzo Colonna</persName>
                    <date when="1672-09-27">September 27 1672</date>
                </bibl>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository key="colonna-archive">
                            Colonna Archive, library of the abbey of Santa Scolastica, Subiaco, Italy
                        </repository>
                        <collection>
                            Lettere di Maria Mancini
                        </collection>
                        <idno type="collection">IICP1</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents facs="DSCF8478;DSCF8479;DSCF8480">
                        <p>Document is one leaf, handwritten on recto and verso.</p>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <extent>
                                    <measure type="composition" unit="leaf" quantity="1">1 leaf</measure>
                                </extent>
                            </supportDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc hands="1">
                            <handNote xml:id="mancini-marie" medium="black">
                                Marie Mancini handwritten
                            </handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origDate when="1672-09-27">September 27 1672</origDate>
                            <origPlace>
                                <placeName key="lys">Lys</placeName>
                            </origPlace>
                        </origin>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
         <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2020-05-28" who="#lrm">
                Initial creation of XML from non-XML electronic files
            </change>
            <change when="2020-06-29" who="#lrm">
                Creation of "edit" file
            </change>
            <change when="2022-03-15" who="#kx">
                Final edit of file
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="letter" xml:id="letter_1672_09_27_mm2lc_raw" n="12" facs="DSCF8478">
                <head type="raw" xml:lang="it" />
                <note resp="#smn" xml:id="archive-note">
                Collocazione II-C.P.1 lettera 12
                Lettere di Maria Mancini – 1672
                Numero d'ordine – 12

                D. Maria Colonna-Mancini –

                =

                Lettera al Contestabile Colonna
                in data	27 Settembre 1672 da Lys
                Sigillo – tutta di pugno –

                oggetto:
                </note>
                <pb facs="DSCF8479"/>
                <note resp="#smn">
                [[The dark ink soaked through the paper so that the images are fairly hard to read.]]
                </note>
                <note resp="#smn">
                [[On the left side of the image, the diagonally folded paper with address written on outside: 
                "A Monsieur
                Monsieur le Conestable 
                Colonna
                Roma"
                + 1 red wax seal]]
                </note>
                <note resp="#smn">
                [[Along the bottom edge of the left side of the paper, parallel with the edge and upside down, is written the date by an archivist or a scretary. The ink looks similar to Marie's ink, except that the lines are thinner than her lines are.]]   
                </note>
                <note resp="#smn">
                [[On the right half of the sheet:]]
                </note>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName>del lys</placeName>
                        <date>li 27 sep[[tembre]] 1672]</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Si avessi il dono di poter [[something crossed out]] mpiciar [[something crossed out]] la gente di parlar allo sproposito ne ritirarei magior vantagio ch' nessuno potete percio creder che quanto si &#233; detto in piemonte &#233; in pariggi circa la triaca non &#233; derivato da me; la gente ignorante dice sempre quello li viene ala bocca; in quanto alla prima letra che vi scrissi circa al sospetto della mia poca salute non intesi per questo di veleno ma piu tosto alterata da inquietudine d'animo et da disgusti ch' mi causava l'o spresso ch' riconoscevo ogni giorno magiore in voi; per quello mio fratello mi diceva non temei</p>
                <pb facs="DSCF8480"/>
                <note resp="#smn">
                [[On the right half of the sheet:]]   
                </note>
                <p>altro. se non qualque disegno di condurmi fuora il resto de miei giorni; sapete quello mavete detto piu volte a solo a solo <hi rend="sup">quando vi pregavo di condurmi a venetia</hi> ch' non volevio [[something crossed out]] <hi rend="sup">Andar</hi> [[something crossed out]] piu per il <hi rend="sup">mondo</hi> [[something crossed out]] per non far le comedie ch'ero il disonor di casa vostra et mille altre cose disobliganti al vivo; per prova di questo se la mia zia mavesse volsuto riccever in casa quella volta que il principe de sonnino ci raccomodo io vi sarei restata per sempre; perche non trovo peggio che viver con un marito <hi rend="sup">che</hi> non si fida di voi et biasima continuamente la vostra condotta; sara tale al avvenir che son certa [[Marie appears to have written "ch'" and then crossed out the "ch'"]] ch' ne sarete satisfatto et sentirete con vostra sodisfatione ch'ognuno la lodara; cosi il vostro
                </p>
                <note resp="#smn">
                [[On the left half of the sheet, turned 90&#xb0;:]]    
                </note>
                <p>sara in salvo; et io avero la consolatione di non sentir piu parlar di me; in quanto poi al torto ch' dite ch' io o fatto colla fuga alla vostra casa; io non pretendo esser fugita altrimente sono andata in compagnia di mia sorella &#233; un servitore non so se si pol andar; piu honoratamente potevo andar con piu decoro per la mia qualita; ma non per la mia riputatione rendetemi almancho questa giustitia &#233; credetemi sempre vostra</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>Maria Mancini Colonna</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <note resp="#smn">
                        [[Added in other ink – thinner lines:]]
                    </note>
                    <p>rimandero andrea con molte galanterie per y miei ragazzi pero vi prego di farlo stare apresso di loro la [[bussiera?]] non essendo bastante per averne cura di tre</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="letter" xml:id="letter_1672_09_27_mm2lc_edit" n="12" facs="DSCF8478">
                <head type="edit" xml:lang="it" />
                <pb facs="DSCF8479"/>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName>Dal Lys</placeName>, 
                        <date>il 27 settembre 1672</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Se avessi il dono di poter impedire la gente dal parlare a sproposito ne ritrarrei maggior vantaggio che nessuno; potete perci&#242; credere che quanto si &#232; detto in Piemonte e in Parigi circa la triaca non &#232; derivato da me. La gente ignorante dice sempre quello che gli viene alla bocca; in quanto alla prima lettera che vi scrissi circa al sospetto della mia poca salute, non intesi per questo il veleno ma piuttosto che ero alterata da inquietudine d'animo e dai disgusti che mi causava lo sprezzo che riconoscevo ogni giorno maggiore in voi; di quello che mio fratello mi diceva non temei</p>
                <pb facs="DSCF8480"/>
                <p>altro, se non qualche disegno di condurmi fuori il resto dei miei giorni. Sapete quello che mi avete detto pi&#249; volte, solo a solo, quando vi pregavo di condurmi a Venezia, che non volevate andar pi&#249; per il mondo per non far commedie, che ero il disonore di casa vostra e mille altre cose <ref type="annotate" xml:id="1672_09_27_mm2lc_a" style="Marie's Italian seems to be colored by her French here. Whereas “disobbligare” in Italian means “to release from an obligation,” her adjective “disobbligante” is meant to be the equivalent of the the French “désobligeant”ー“unkind” or “disagreeable.”">disobbliganti</ref> al vivo; per prova di questo, se la mia zia mi avesse voluto ricevere, quella volta che il principe di Sonnino ci raccomod&#242;, io vi sarei restata per sempre; perch&#232; non trovo peggio che vivere con un marito che non si fida di voi e biasima continuamente la vostra condotta. Essa sar&#224; tale in avvenire che son certa che ne sarete soddisfatto e sentirete con vostra soddisfazione che ognuno la loder&#224;; cos&#236; il vostro sar&#224; in salvo ed io avr&#242; la consolazione di non sentir pi&#249; parlar di me; in quanto poi al torto che dite che io ho fatto alla vostra casa con la fuga: io non pretendo d'esser fuggita; altrimenti, sono andata in compagnia di mia sorella e di un servitore; non so se si pu&#242; andar pi&#249; onorabilmente. Potevo andar con pi&#249; decoro per la mia qualit&#224; ma non per la mia reputazione. Rendetemi almeno questa giustizia e credetemi sempre vostra.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute></salute>
                    <signed>Maria Mancini Colonna</signed>.
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Rimander&#242; Andrea con molte galanterie per i miei ragazzi per&#242; vi prego di farlo stare presso di loro, la Bussiera non essendo bastante per avere cura di tre.</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="letter" xml:id="letter_1672_09_27_mm2lc_translation" n="12" facs="DSCF8478">
                <head type="translation" xml:lang="en" />
                <pb facs="DSCF8479"/>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName key="lys">The Lys</placeName>, 
                        <date when="1672-09-27">27 September 1672</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>If I had the gift of being able to keep people from running their mouths, I would take greater advantage of it than anyone; so you can be sure that what has been said in Piedmont or in Paris about <ref type="annotate" xml:id="1672_09_27_mm2lc_b" style="Theriac was a pharmaceutical preparation used as an antidote to poison.">theriac</ref> did not come from me. Ignorant people always say whatever comes into their mouths. As for the first letter I wrote you, concerning the doubts I had about my poor health, I didn't mean to imply poison by that, but rather that I was upset by the anxiety and disgust your contempt caused me–the contempt I could see growing stronger in you every day. As for what my brother used to tell me, I didn't fear anything</p>
                <pb facs="DSCF8480"/>
                <p>except some scheme to put me away for the rest of my days. You know what you said to me many times in private, when I begged you to take me to Venice: that you didn't want to go out in society anymore so you wouldn't have to put on an act, that I was a disgrace to your family, and a thousand other deeply hurtful things. As proof of it, if my aunt had been willing to take me in, that time when the Prince of Sonnino patched things up between us, I would have stayed there forever; because I cannot think of anything worse than living with a husband who doesn't trust you and who constantly criticizes your conduct. In the future, it will be such that I am certain you will be pleased with it, and you will get the satisfaction of having everyone praise it. That way, your honor will be safe, and I will have the consolation of hearing no more talk about me. And as for the harm you say I did to your family by running away: I do not claim to have run away; rather, I went in the company of my sister and a servant; I don't know if it's possible to go any more honorably. I could have gone with greater dignity for the sake of my rank, but not of my reputation.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>Do me at least that justice, and believe me to be ever yours.</salute>
                    <signed><persName key="mancini-marie">Maria Mancini Colonna</persName></signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>I will send Andrea back with lots of presents for my boys, but I ask you to have him stay with them, since la <ref type="annotate" xml:id="1672_09_27_mm2lc_c" style="La Bussiera: Marie is referring to a woman servant by her family name.">Bussiera</ref> can't manage alone to take care of all three.</postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
