<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>lett 47 Marie to Lorenzo</title>
                <author key="mancini-marie">Marie Mancini</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcribed and translated by</resp>
                    <name xml:id="smn">Sarah M. Nelson</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Edited by</resp>
                    <name xml:id="am">Alessandro Martina</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoded by</resp>
                    <name xml:id="lrm">Liam R. Marchant</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>The Correspondence of Marie Mancini</authority>
                <publisher>University of Idaho Library</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>https://thecdil.github.io/mancini_source/</addrLine>
                </address>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Inquiry and Learning</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Room 211</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Idaho Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Moscow, ID 83844-2350</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>https://cdil.lib.uidaho.edu/</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2020</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>The Correspondence of Marie Mancini is freely distributed by the Center for Digital Inquiry and Learning at the University of Idaho Library and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-ND 4.0) United States License.
                    </p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note>Marie informs Lorenzo of her forced residence in the Antwerp citadel. She brings up the potential political implications on the House of Colonna from this action and implores Lorenzo to intervene. She claims that this position she is in is a result of the Marquis of Borgomanero getting back at her for disagreements they shared on the road.</note>
            </notesStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Correspondence of Marie Mancini</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title key="1673_12_29_mm2lc" type="letter" n="47">lett 47 Marie to Lorenzo</title>
                    <author key="mancini-marie">Marie Mancini</author>
                    <persName type="addressee" key="colonna-lorenzo">Lorenzo Colonna</persName>
                    <date when="1673-12-29">December 29 1673</date>
                </bibl>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository key="colonna-archive">
                            Colonna Archive, library of the abbey of Santa Scolastica, Subiaco, Italy
                        </repository>
                        <collection>
                            Lettere di Maria Mancini
                        </collection>
                        <idno type="collection">IICP1</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents facs="DSCF8573;DSCF8574;DSCF8575;DSCF8576">
                        <p>Document is one leaf, handwritten on recto and verso.</p>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <extent>
                                    <measure type="composition" unit="leaf" quantity="1">1 leaf</measure>
                                </extent>
                            </supportDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc hands="1">
                            <handNote xml:id="mancini-marie" medium="black">
                                Marie Mancini handwritten
                            </handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origDate when="1673-12-29">December 29 1673</origDate>
                            <origPlace>
                                <placeName key="antwerp">Antwerp</placeName>
                            </origPlace>
                        </origin>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>
                    </p>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2020-06-08" who="#lrm">
                Initial creation of XML from non-XML electronic files
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="letter" xml:id="letter_1673_12_29_mm2lc_raw" n="47" facs="DSCF8573">
                <head type="raw" xml:lang="it" />
                <note resp="#smn" xml:id="archive-note">
                Collocazione II-C.P.1. lettera 47
                Lettere di Maria Mancini – 1673
                Numero d'ordine – 29

                D. Maria Colonna-Mancini –

                =

                Lettera al Contestabile Colonna
                in data	29 Dicembre 1673 da Anversa
                Sigillo mancante – tutta di pugno –

                oggetto:
                </note>
                <pb facs="DSCF8574"/>
                <note resp="#smn">
                [[Image is a sheet 15 cm wide; this first page of the letter and the second and third pages are a single sheet, folded booklet-style in the middle]]  
                </note>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        danvers
                        <date when="1673-12-29">ce 29<hi rend="sup">me</hi>decem[[bre]] 1673</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Doppo aver inviato la letra che mi scriveste al marquese di Borgomenero [[<hi rend="strike">per</hi>]] accio potesse servir d'autentica al conte de monterey ch'[[<hi rend="strike">ion</hi>]] io sono in questi paesi con vostra aprovatione, luy mi rispose che non era a proposito quella letra da far veddere al conte ne tanpoco era tempo allora di parlar a Sus E di alcun negotio ma se troveria occasione che non mancheria de servirme, mi a fatto un tiro il marquese che nol averia mai creso perche de malines io venni ancor qua su la sua parola credendo andar nella citta d'anversa in casa del governatore &#233; desser libera comforme mi promese &#233; non star rinchiusa nel castello con guardie sensa esser <hi rend="sup">poter</hi> [[<hi rend="strike">libera d</hi>]]'uscir dela cammera credetemi che non &#233; [[Marie first wrote "o" and then wrote &#233; over it]] riputatione vostra ne de i nostri figli ch'io stia rinchiusa</p>
                <pb facs="DSCF8575"/>
                <note resp="#smn">
                [[This is the left side of what would be the image of the opened-up sheet—the verso of image DSCF8574—with writing turned 90&#xb0;. It is the third and final page of the letter—see transcription below.]]    
                </note>
                <pb facs="DSCF8576"/>
                <note resp="#smn">
                [[The image is the right side of what would be the opened-up sheet.]]
                </note>
                <note resp="#smn">
                [[You can see writing on the reverse side of this sheet. If the image of the first page of the letter had been the full opened-up sheet as with most of the letters, this writing would have been along the left edge of the sheet, parallel with the edge. It appears to be the place and date, written by an archivist or a secretary.]]
                </note>
                <p>per forsa in una cittadella pero scrivete al conte come voi vi contentate ch io stia in brusselles in un convento comforme avete deia scritto a me non potendo desiderar davantaggio ne vi fate rimovere perche vi assicuro che vi &#233; molta malignita [something crossed out] contra di me ne posso dirvi ogni cosa perche temo che le letre siano tutte viste ma siate certo qu'averete sempre magior campo di lodorvi di me quando vi contentarete di compiacermi nelle cose ragionevoli come sono queste che desidero adesso da voi per farmi preiuditio <hi rend="sup">li maligni</hi> sono andati dicendo ch'io ricevo pensione del Re di francia &#233; che sono qua d'ordine suo vedete se <hi rend="sup">se</hi> puole inventare niente di peggio io o risposto ch'&#233; vero ch'[[<hi rend="strike">iol</hi>]] il Re ma assistito ma ch'essendo in fiandra questo non sara &#233; ch'allora averan sugetto di dolersi <hi rend="sup">di me</hi> se ricevessi pensione da luy ma <hi rend="sup">che</hi> avanti io non rendevo conto a loro delle mie actioni. oliva &#233; ancora</p>
                <pb facs="DSCF8575"/>
                <note resp="#smn">
                [[This is the left side of what would be the image of the opened-up sheet—the verso of image DSCF8574—with writing turned 90&#xb0;. It is the third and final page of the letter.]]
                </note>
                <p>a brusselles vi prego se viene a Roma di non farli molta acogliensa che vi protesto che no lo merita &#233; sono certa che non si <hi rend="sup">puol</hi> corispondere verso di me con magior ingratitudine don mauritio &#233; testimonio quello ch'io o speso per luy a turino &#233; martino per il viaggio, si ponno veder i conti, &#233; con tutto cio non era mai contento, &#233; si vergognava di dir ch'era servitor mio adesso. &#233; tutto del marquese, lor dui soli ognun lo sa, manno fatto questo bel gioco di farmi entrar qui dentro avendomi tradito tutti dui per vendicarsi di [[Marie first wrote "de" and then changed it to "di"]] qualche contrasto ch'o auto per strada con loro [[a series of 4 or 5 words crossed out]] non averia mai creso <hi rend="sup">il marquese</hi> cosi vindicativo, ricordatevi che sono moglie vostra &#233; che non &#233; di riputatione della vostra casa ch io stia altrove che in un monasterio adio scriveteme spesso &#233; assicurateve che non o magior consolatione</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>M. M. C.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter" xml:id="letter_1673_12_29_mm2lc_edit" n="47" facs="DSCF8573">
                <head type="edit" xml:lang="it" />
                <pb facs="DSCF8574"/>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName key="antwerp">D'Anvers</placeName>, 
                        <date when="1673-12-29">ce 29 d&#233;cembre <ref type="annotate" xml:id="1673_12_29_mm2lc_a" style="Note that Marie's Italian is influenced by her French, and she often writes the dates of her Italian letters in French.">1673</ref></date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Dopo aver inviato la lettera che mi scriveste al marchese di Borgomanero, acci&#242; potesse servir ad autenticare al conte di Monterey che io sono in questi paesi con la vostra approvazione, lui mi rispose che non era a proposito, quella lettera, da far vedere al Conte; n&#233; tampoco era tempo allora di parlare a Sua Eccellenza di alcun negozio ma, se trovasse occasione, che non mancherebbe di servirmi. Mi ha fatto un <ref type="annotate" xml:id="1673_12_29_mm2lc_a" style="The meaning is 'mi ha giocato un tiro.'">tiro</ref> il Marchese che non avrei mai creduto; perch&#233; da Malines io venni ancora qua sulla sua parola, credendo di andare nella citt&#224; di Anversa, in casa del governatore, e di esser libera conforme mi promise, e non di star rinchiusa nel castello con guardie senza poter uscire dalla camera. Credetemi che non &#232; reputazione vostra n&#233; dei nostri figli che io stia rinchiusa</p>
                <pb facs="DSCF8575"/>
                <pb facs="DSCF8576"/>
                <p>per forza in una cittadella; perci&#242; scrivete al Conte che voi vi contentate che io stia a Bruxelles in un convento, conforme avete gi&#224; scritto a me, non potendo desiderare di pi&#249;, n&#233; vi fate rimuovere da questa idea, perch&#233; vi assicuro che vi &#232; molta malignit&#224; contro di me, n&#233; posso dirvi ogni cosa perch&#233; temo che le lettere siano tutte viste; ma siate certo che avrete sempre maggior campo di lodarvi di me, quando vi contenterete di compiacermi nelle cose ragionevoli come sono queste che desidero adesso da voi. Per farmi pregiudizio i maligni sono andati dicendo che io ricevo una pensione dal Re di Francia, e che sono qua per ordine suo. Vedete se si pu&#242; inventare niente di peggio; io ho risposto che &#232; vero che il Re mi ha assistito, ma che essendo in Fiandra questo non accadr&#224; pi&#249; e che se ricevessi una pensione da lui in futuro, all&#243;ra avrebbero motivo di dolersi di me, ma che prima io non rendevo conto a loro delle mie azioni. Oliva &#232; ancora</p>
                <pb facs="DSCF8575"/>
                <p>a Bruxelles; vi prego, se viene a Roma, di non fargli molta accoglienza, che vi protesto che non lo merita, e sono certa che non si pu&#242; corrispondere verso di me con maggior ingratitudine; don Maurizio &#232; testimone di quello che io ho speso per lui a Torino, e Martino di quello che ho speso per lui durante il viaggio: si possono vedere i conti; e con tutto ci&#242;, non era mai contento e si vergognava di dire che era servitor mio adesso. &#232; tutto del Marchese, loro due soli, ognun lo sa, mi hanno fatto questo bel gioco di farmi entrare qui dentro, avendomi tradito tutti e due per vendicarsi di qualche contrasto che ho avuto per strada con loro. Non avrei mai creduto il Marchese così vendicativo; ricordatevi che sono moglie vostra e che non &#232; di reputazione della vostra casa che io stia altrove che in un monastero. Addio, scrivetemi spesso e restate sicuro che non ho maggior consolazione.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>M. M. C.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter" xml:id="letter_1673_12_29_mm2lc_translation" n="47" facs="DSCF8573">
                <head type="translation" xml:lang="en" />
                <pb facs="DSCF8574"/>
            <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName key="antwerp">Antwerp</placeName>, 
                        <date when="1673-12-29">29 December 1673</date>
                    </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>After having sent the letter that you wrote me to the <persName key="borgomanero">Marquis of Borgomanero</persName>, so that it could serve to prove to the <persName key="monterey">Count of Monterey</persName> that I am in this country with your approval, he replied to me that it was not appropriate to show that letter to the count, not was it the right time to speak to His Excellency about any negotiation, but if he found an opportune moment, he would not fail to serve me. The marquis played a trick on me that I would never have believed; because from <placeName key="mechelen">Mechelen</placeName> I came along to here on the strength of his word, believing I was going to the city of <placeName key="antwerp">Antwerp</placeName>, to the house of the governor, and that I was free as he had promised me, and not that I would be locked up in the castle with guards, unable to leave my room. Believe me that it is not good for your reputation nor that of our children for me to be locked up</p>
            <pb facs="DSCF8575"/>
            <pb facs="DSCF8576"/>
            <p>by force in a citadel; so write to the count that you are satisfied that I be in <placeName key="brussels">Brussels</placeName> in a convent, as you have already written to me, since you can desire no more, and do not let yourself be moved from that idea, because I assure you that there is a lot of malevolence towards me, and I cannot tell you everything because I fear that the letters are all seen; but you can be certain that you will have ever greater cause to be pleased with me when you agree to gratify me in reasonable things such as those I desire of you now. In order to do me ill, malicious people have gone about saying that I receive a pension from the King of <placeName key="france">France</placeName>, and that I am here on his orders. Can you imagine inventing anything worse? I've replied that it is true the King has assisted me, but now that I am in Flanders that will not happen anymore, and that if I were to receive a pension from him in the future, then they would have reason to complain about me, but that before, I did not answer to them for my actions. <persName key="oliva-gian-paolo">Oliva</persName> is still</p>
            <pb facs="DSCF8575"/>
            <p>in <placeName key="brussels">Brussels</placeName>; I beg you, if he comes to <placeName key="rome">Rome</placeName>, to not give him a warm reception, which I declare to you he does not deserve, and I am certain that it's impossible to behave more ungratefully towards me. <persName key="bologna-maurizio">Don Maurizio</persName> can attest to what I spent for him in <placeName key="turin">Turin</placeName>, and Martino, to what I spent for him during the journey: you can see the accounts; and even so, he was never satisfied, and he was embarrassed to say that he was in my service now. He is all for the marquis—the two of them alone, everyone knows, played this fine prank on me of making me come into this place, having deceived me, both of them, to take revenge for some disagreement I had with them on the road. I would never have believed the marquis was so vindictive; remember that I am your wife and that it does not help the reputation of your house for me to be elsewhere than in a convent.</p>
            <closer>
                    <salute>Farewell, write to me often and rest assured that I have no greater consolation.</salute>
                    <signed><persName key="mancini-marie">M. M. C.</persName></signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
