<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>lett 33 Marie to Lorenzo</title>
                <author key="mancini-marie">Marie Mancini</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcribed and translated by</resp>
                    <name xml:id="smn">Sarah M. Nelson</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Edited by</resp>
                    <name xml:id="am">Alessandro Martina</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoded by</resp>
                    <name xml:id="omw">Olivia M. Wikle</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>The Correspondence of Marie Mancini</authority>
                <publisher>University of Idaho Library</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>https://thecdil.github.io/mancini_source/</addrLine>
                </address>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Inquiry and Learning</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Room 211</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Idaho Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Moscow, ID 83844-2350</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>https://cdil.lib.uidaho.edu/</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2020</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>The Correspondence of Marie Mancini is freely distributed by the Center for Digital Inquiry and Learning at the University of Idaho Library and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-ND 4.0) United States License.
                    </p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note>Marie persists in seeing that her 30 plots of mountain land are sold and asks Lorenzo to go through with this on her behalf. She desires to return to her family in Paris.</note>
            </notesStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Correspondence of Marie Mancini</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title key="1673_08_07_mm2lc" type="letter" n="33">lett 33 Marie to Lorenzo</title>
                    <author key="mancini-marie">Marie Mancini</author>
                    <persName type="addressee" key="lorenzo">Lorenzo</persName>
                    <date when="1673-08-07">August 7 1673</date>
                </bibl>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository key="colonna-archive">
                            Colonna Archive, library of the abbey of Santa Scolastica, Subiaco, Italy
                        </repository>
                        <collection>
                            Lettere di Maria Mancini
                        </collection>
                        <idno type="collection">IICP1</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents facs="DSCF8532;DSCF8533;DSCF8534">
                        <p>Document is one leaf, handwritten on recto and verso.</p>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <extent>
                                    <measure type="composition" unit="leaf" quantity="1">1 leaf</measure>
                                </extent>
                            </supportDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc hands="1">
                            <handNote xml:id="mancini-marie" medium="black">
                                Marie Mancini handwritten
                            </handNote>
                            <handNote xml:id="unk" medium="black">
                                Secretary or archivist
                            </handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origDate when="1673-08-07">August 7 1673</origDate>
                            <origPlace>
                                <placeName key="turin">Turin</placeName>
                            </origPlace>
                        </origin>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>
                        The archive incorrectly labeled this letter with date 1673-08-01. The correct date is 1673-08-07.
                    </p>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2020-05-17" who="#omw">
                Initial creation of XML from non-XML electronic files
            </change>
            <change when="2020-07-27" who="#omw">
                Raw and edit div changes
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="letter" xml:id="letter_1673_08_07_mm2lc_raw" n="33" facs="DSCF8532">
                <head type="raw" xml:lang="it" />
                <note resp="#smn" xml:id="archive-note">
                    Collocazione II-C.P.1. lett. 33
                    Lett. di Maria Mancini – 1673
                    Nr d'ordine – 16
                    
                    D. Maria Colonna-Mancini –
                    
                    =
                    
                    Lettera al Contestabile Colonna
                    in data	1&#xb0; [[actually 7]] Agosto 1673 da Torino
                    Sigillo mancante – tutta di pugno –
                    oggetto:
                </note>
                <pb facs="DSCF8533"/>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        di torino
                        <date when="1673-08-04">li 4 agosto 1673</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <note resp="#smn">
                    [[On the left side of the image, just to the left of the center fold, parallel with the fold, is written the date by an archivist or a secretary, and it appears to say "7 Agosto 73." The ink looks similar to Marie's ink, but the lines are thicker, more absorbed into the paper.]]
                </note>
                <note resp="#smn">
                    [[On the right half of the sheet:]]
                </note>
                <p>Don mauritio mi a parlato con dirme la bonta che mostrate verso di me; pero continuo a scrivervi [[Marie appears to have changed "scrivermi" to "scrivervi" by crossing out the last down stroke of the word and dotting the downstroke before it, to make it an "i"]] &#233; a ringratiarvene come faro sempre mentre conoscero che le mie letre vi diano gusto. in quanto poi a quello volete sapere circa il monasterio che desidero, io averei volsuto portarmi de qua a drittura a pariggi in una abadia ma poi che voi no lo giudicate a proposito, per adesso mi trattero, nel convento del lys, se me lo vorranno permettere; se no a lione aux ursule <hi rend="sup">a la rue de la vieille monoye</hi> [[something crossed out underneath—it looks like it might possibly have included "bellecour"]]. &#233; fra tanto voi farete ogni sforso accio il Re in gratia vostra non mi neghi questa consolatione di star in un convento a pariggi tra i</p>
                <pb facs="DSCF8534"/>
                <note resp="#smn">[[On the right half of the sheet:]]</note>
                <p>miei parenti. &#233; perche considero benissimo che per la spesa di questo viaggio vi vorra di denari assai particolarmente se me acompagna il marquese di borgomenero, come dice di voler fare, stimo per bene che non avendone voi bona somma di contanti &#233; pronti vi contentiate che si vendino trenta lochi de miei monti per questo effetto; et questi denari le potrete far rimettere quy a don mauritio il quale potra venir con me se vi contentate che mi serrva in nome vostro accio mi soministi poi in convento in francia quella assistensa che mi fate gratia adesso; et come credo che per vender i trenta luochi de miei monti cammerali costi vi sara necessario sensa dubbio il mio consentimento et autorita per farlo</p>
                <note resp="#smn">[[On the left half of the sheet, turned 90 degrees:]]</note>
                <p>tutto questo la do in virtu di questa mia letra a voi afinche con la <hi rend="strike">mia</hi> vostra autorita in Roma, et questa mia volonta ordiniate a marcatelli. o a chi vorrete le vendano</p>
                <p>Maria Mancini Colonna</p>
                <note resp="#smn">[[A blank space equal to about 4 or 5 lines' worth, then more writing:]]</note>
                <p>solamente per non disgustarvi mi tratengo ancora qua dove <hi rend="strike">sto</hi> mi vedo di mala voglia &#233; con ragione. pero subito ch averete risposta del Re fatemelo sapere perche in quanto poi alla licensa del entrar in monasterio ogni archivescovo del loco <hi rend="sup">me la</hi> pol dare. sollecitate ancho il denaro &#233; in caso non si possano vender cosi presto potete farveli prestare [[something crossed out]] accio sia rimesso qui prontamente per pagare quello devo et con</p>
                <note resp="#smn">[[On the left half of the sheet, along the top edge, written upside down relative to the writing on the right half of the sheet:]]</note>
                <closer>
                    <salute>questo mi confermo sempre vostra</salute>
                    <signed>M. M. C.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter" xml:id="letter_1673_08_07_mm2lc_edit" n="33" facs="DSCF8532">
                <head type="edit" xml:lang="it" />
                <pb facs="DSCF8533"/>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        Da Torino
                        <date when="1673-08-07">il 7 agosto 1673</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Don Maurizio mi ha parlato per dirmi la bont&#224; che mostrate verso di me; perci&#242; continuo a scrivervi e a ringraziarvene come far&#242; sempre mentre conoscer&#242; che le mie lettere vi diano gusto. In quanto poi a quello che volete sapere circa il monastero che desidero, io avrei voluto portarmi da qua addirittura a Parigi in una bad&#236;a. Ma poich&#233; voi non lo giudicate a proposito, per adesso mi tratterr&#242; nel convento del Lys, se me lo vorranno permettere; se no a Lione presso le  Orsoline della via Vieille-Monnaie. E frattanto, voi farete ogni sforzo affinch&#242; il Re in grazia vostra non mi neghi questa consolazione di stare in un convento a Parigi tra i</p>
                <pb facs="DSCF8534"/>
                <p>miei parenti. E perch&#233; considero benissimo che per la spesa di questo viaggio ci vorr&#224; parecchio denaro, particolarmente se mi accompagna il marchese di Borgomanero, come dice di voler fare, stimo per bene che non avendone voi buona somma di contanti e pronti, vi contentiate che si vendano trenta lochi dei miei monti per questo effetto. E questi denari, li potrete far rimettere qui a don Maurizio, il quale potr&#224; venire con me se vi contentate che mi serva in nome vostro, affinch&#233; mi somministri poi in convento in Francia quella assistenza che mi fate grazia adesso. E siccome credo che per vendere i trenta lochi dei miei monti camerali vi sar&#224; necessario senza dubbio il mio consenso e autorit&#224; per farlo, tutto questo lo do in virt&#249; di questa mia lettera a voi affinch&#233; con la vostra autorit&#224; in Roma, e questa mia volont&#224;, ordiniate a Marcatelli, o a chi vorrete, che li vendano.</p>
                <p>Maria Mancini Colonna</p>
                <p>Solamente per non disgustarvi mi trattengo ancora qua dove mi vedo di mala voglia e con ragione. Per&#242; subito che avrete risposta dal Re, fatemelo sapere, affinch&#233;, in quanto poi alla licenza dell'entrare in monastero, ogni arcivescovo del loco me la possa dare. Sollecitate anche il denaro e in caso non si possano vendere cos&#236; presto, potete farvelo prestare affinch&#233; sia rimesso qui prontamente per pagare quello che devo.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>E con questo mi confermo sempre vostra.</salute>
                    <signed>M. M. C.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter" xml:id="letter_1673_08_07_mm2lc_translation" n="33" facs="DSCF8532">
                <head type="translation" xml:lang="en" />
                <pb facs="DSCF8533"/>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName key="turin"><ref type="annotate" xml:id="1673_08_07_mm2lc_a" style="In the seventeenth century, Turin was the capital of the Duchy of Savoy, which was a state subject to the Holy Roman Empire. The territory of the Duchy of Savoy covered parts of what are now France and Italy. Both Marie and her sister Hortense were the beneficiaries of the Duke of Savoy's hospitality—Marie in Turin, and Hortense in Chambéry. The Duke had been one of Hortense's suitors before her marriage, and he gave her the use of his residence in Chambéry from her arrival there in 1672 until his untimely death in 1675.">Turin</ref></placeName>
                        <date when="1673-08-07">4 August 1673</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p><persName key="bologna-maurizio"><ref type="annotate" xml:id="1673_08_07_mm2lc_b" style="Don Maurizio Bologna had been Marie's Italian secretary in Rome, and he was sent to her in Turin by Lorenzo in late February 1673, more to spy on her than to serve her. --Dulong, Marie Mancini, 233-37.">Don Maurizio</ref></persName> has spoken to me and told me of the kindness you are showing toward me; and thus I continue to write to you and thank you for it, as I will always do so long as I know that my letters bring you pleasure. As for what you wish to know about the monastery I want, I would have liked to go directly from here to <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName>, to an abbey. But since that does not meet with your approval, for now I will stay in the <placeName key="lys"><ref type="annotate" xml:id="1673_08_07_mm2lc_c" n="3" style="The Cistercian abbey Notre Dame du Lys was located in Dammarie-lès-Lys, near Melun, 40 miles southeast of Paris. It was a royal abbey which housed young girls of prominent families and women protected by the crown. Founded in 1244 by Saint Louis and his mother, Blanche de Castille, it was destroyed by fire in 1358 during the Hundred Years War, rebuilt starting in the fifteenth century, and destroyed again during the Revolution. Only ruins remain today.">convent Du Lys</ref></placeName>, if they are willing to let me stay there; otherwise, in <placeName key="lyon">Lyon</placeName> with the Ursulines in the <placeName key="monnaie">rue Vieille-Monnaie</placeName>. And in the meantime, you will make every effort to see that the <persName key="louis-xiv">King</persName>, as a favor to you, does not deny me this consolation of staying in a convent in <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName> near</p>
                <pb facs="DSCF8534"/>
                <p>my family. And since I can well imagine that it will take quite a lot of money to cover the expense of this journey, particularly if the <persName key="borgomanero"><ref type="annotate" xml:id="1673_08_07_mm2lc_d" style="Prince Don Carlo Emanuele d'Este, Marquis de Borgomanero (1622-1695), was, like Lorenzo Onofrio Colonna, an Italian nobleman in the service of Spain. He was a grandee of Spain and a knight of the Order of the Golden Fleece, and he later became the viceroy of Galicia, a conseiller d'État, and the king of Spain's ambassador to England and to the Holy Roman Emperor. Borgomanero also had close family connections to the dukes of Savoy, as his father had been in their service.">Marquis de Borgomanero</ref></persName> accompanies me as he says he would like to do, I think it well that, as you do not have a great deal of ready cash, you should see fit that thirty plots of land of my mountains be sold for this purpose. And you can have those funds transferred here to <persName key="bologna-maurizio">Don Maurizio</persName>, who will be able to come with me, if it pleases you that he serve me on your behalf, in order to administer to me in the convent in <placeName key="france">France</placeName> the assistance that you are graciously providing now. And since I believe that to sell the thirty plots of land of my mountains, you will no doubt need my consent and authority, I give those to you by virtue of the present letter, so that using your authority in <placeName key="rome">Rome</placeName>, and according to my wishes here stated, you may order <persName key="marcatelli"><ref type="annotate" xml:id="1673_08_07_mm2lc_e" style="Marcatelli was a servant of the Colonna household in Rome whom Marie often mentions in connection with financial transactions.">Marcatelli</ref></persName> or whomever you wish, to sell them.</p>
                <p><persName key="mancini-marie">Maria Mancini Colonna</persName></p>
                <p>It is only to avoid displeasing you that I remain here, where I am reluctant to stay and with good reason. But as soon as you have a reply from the <persName key="louis-xiv">King</persName>, let me know so that the archbishop of whichever place will be able to give me permission to enter the monastery. Press for the money, too, and if the land cannot be sold that quickly, you can have it lent to you so that it can be transferred here right away to pay what I owe.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>And with that, I assure you that I am ever your</salute>
                    <signed><persName key="mancini-marie">M. M. C.</persName></signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
