<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>lett 2 Marie to Lorenzo</title>
                <author key="mancini-marie">Marie Mancini</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcribed and translated by</resp>
                    <name xml:id="smn">Sarah M. Nelson</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Edited by</resp>
                    <name xml:id="am">Alessandro Martina</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoded by</resp>
                    <name xml:id="lrm">Liam R. Marchant</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>The Correspondence of Marie Mancini</authority>
                <publisher>University of Idaho Library</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>https://thecdil.github.io/mancini_source/</addrLine>
                </address>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Inquiry and Learning</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Room 211</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Idaho Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Moscow, ID 83844-2350</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>https://cdil.lib.uidaho.edu/</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2020</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>The Correspondence of Marie Mancini is freely distributed by the Center for Digital Inquiry and Learning at the University of Idaho Library and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-ND 4.0) United States License.
                    </p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note>Marie once again proclaims her aversion to returning to Rome and requests one of her sons be sent to learn from Monsieur Boniel.</note>
            </notesStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Correspondence of Marie Mancini</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title key="1673_01_14_mm2lc" type="letter" n="02">lett 2 Marie to Lorenzo</title>
                    <author key="mancini-marie">Marie Mancini</author>
                    <persName type="addressee" key="colonna-lorenzo">Lorenzo Colonna</persName>
                    <date when="1673-01-14">January 14 1673</date>
                </bibl>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository key="colonna-archive">
                            Colonna Archive, library of the abbey of Santa Scolastica, Subiaco, Italy
                        </repository>
                        <collection>
                            Lettere di Maria Mancini
                        </collection>
                        <idno type="collection">IICP1</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents facs="DSCF8466;DSCF8467;DSCF8468">
                        <p>Document is one leaf, handwritten on recto and verso.</p>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <extent>
                                    <measure type="composition" unit="leaf" quantity="1">1 leaf</measure>
                                </extent>
                            </supportDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc hands="1">
                            <handNote xml:id="mancini-marie" medium="black">
                                Marie Mancini handwritten
                            </handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origDate when="1673-01-14">January 14 1673</origDate>
                            <origPlace>
                                <placeName key="lyon">Lyon</placeName>
                            </origPlace>
                        </origin>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>
                        The archive incorrectly labels this letter with date 1672-01-14. The correct date is 1673-01-14.
                    </p>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2020-06-15" who="#lrm">
                Initial creation of XML from non-XML electronic files
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="letter" xml:id="letter_1673_01_14_mm2lc_raw" n="02" facs="DSCF8466">
                <head type="raw" xml:lang="it" />
                <note resp="#smn" xml:id="archive-note">
                Collocazione II-C.P.1. lettera 2
                Lettere di Maria Mancini – <hi rend="strike">1672</hi> 1673
                Numero d'ordine – 2

                D. Maria Colonna-Mancini –

                =

                Lettera al Contestabile Colonna
                in data	14 Gennaio 1672 [[actually 1673–date is corrected above on the card]] da Lione
                Sigillo – tutta di pugno –

                oggetto:
                </note>
                <note resp="#smn">
                [[At the bottom of the card is written in pencil: "16720001 – 3".]]
                </note>
                <pb facs="DSCF8467"/>
                <note resp="#smn">
                [[On the left side of the image, the rectangularly folded paper with address written on outside: 
                "A Monsieur
                Monsieur le 
                Constable Colonne
                A Rome"
                + 1 red wax seal]]
                </note>
                <note resp="#smn">
                [[Along the left edge of the left side of the paper, parallel with the edge, is written the date by an archivist or a secretary. The ink looks different from Marie's ink.]]    
                </note>
                <note resp="#smn">
                [[On the right half of the sheet:]]   
                </note>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        lione
                        <date when="1673-01-14">il 14 gennaro 1672 [[the year should be 1673]]</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>non dubito che non siate per aver piena sodisfactione di vedermi ripigliar la volta d'italia lasso la francia sensa disgusto; faro la prima posa a thurino se pero ritrovo il duca portato a [[<hi rend="sup">protege</hi>]] favorirmi; con pensiero di metermi la in un monasterio; so che voi non desideravio altro se non que [[<hi rend="strike">i</hi>]]abandonassi la francia cerco d'incontrar il vostro gusto; potrei anche passar a milano ma non sono ancor certa se volete [[<hi rend="strike">me</hi>]] mandarmi un de miei ragazzi quello avera piu volonta di venirme a trovar potrete mandarlo in letigua questo febraro con una donna M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> boniel avera poi cura di ameastrarlo nelli studi a guisa d'un secondo lotti et tratanto credetemi [[? end of the word is torn out from where the seal was broken]] ch' la magior dificol</p>
                <pb facs="DSCF8468"/>
                <note resp="#smn">
                [[on the right half of the sheet:]]   
                </note>
                <p>ta ch' ritrovo in me &#233; di superar l'aversione che o di tornare in Roma pregaro dio per vostra consolatione que me la levi; non cessando encor che lontana di esser sempre vostra</p>  
                <closer>
                    <signed>Maria Mancini Colonna</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter" xml:id="letter_1673_01_14_mm2lc_edit" n="02" facs="DSCF8466">
                <head type="edit" xml:lang="it" />
                <pb facs="DSCF8467"/>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        Lione, 
                        <date when="1673-01-14">il 14 gennaio 1672</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Non dubito che non siate per aver piena soddisfazione di vedermi ripigliar la volta dell'Italia, lascio la Francia senza disgusto; far&#242; la prima posa a Torino (se trovo il duca portato a favorirmi), con il pensiero di mettermi l&#224; in un monastero; so che voi non desideravate altro se non che abbandonassi la Francia; cerco d'incontrar il vostro gusto. Potrei anche andare a Milano, ma non sono ancora certa se volete mandarmi uno de miei ragazzi, quello che avr&#224; pi&#249; volont&#224; di venirmi a trovare; potrete mandarlo in lettiga questo febbraio con una donna. Monsieur Boniel avr&#224; poi cura di ammaestrarlo negli studi a guisa di un secondo Lotti; e frattanto credetemi che la maggior difficol-</p>
                <pb facs="DSCF8468"/>
                <p>t&#224; che ritrovo in me, &#232; di superare l'avversione che ho di tornare a Roma.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>Pregher&#242; Dio che, per vostra consolazione, me la levi. Non cessando ancora che lontana di esser sempre vostra,</salute>
                    <signed>Maria Mancini Colonna</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter" xml:id="letter_1673_01_14_mm2lc_translation" n="02" facs="DSCF8466">
                <head type="translation" xml:lang="en" />
                <pb facs="DSCF8467"/>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName key="lyon">Lyon</placeName>, 
                        <date when="1673-01-14">14 January 1673</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener> 
                <p>I have no doubt that you are going to be very satisfied to see me return once more to Italy, and I feel no disgust about leaving France. I will make my first stop in <placeName key="turin">Turin</placeName> (if I find the Duke inclined to support me), with the idea of moving into a convent there. I know that your one desire was that I leave France; I am trying to meet your wishes. I could also go to <placeName key="milan">Milan</placeName>, but I am not yet sure whether you are willing to send me one of my boys, whichever of them wants the most to come and join me. You can send him by sedan chair this February with one of the women. Then Monsieur <persName key="boniel">Boniel</placeName> will take care of instructing him in his studies like a second Lotti. In the meantime, please believe that what I find most difficult</p>
                <pb facs="DSCF8468"/>
                <p>is to overcome my aversion to returning to <placeName key="rome">Rome</placeName>.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>I will pray to God that, for your consolation, He will relieve me of it, never ceasing, though I am far away, to be ever yours,</salute>
                    <signed><persName key="mancini-marie">Maria Mancini Colonna</persName></signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
