<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>lett 45 Marie to Lorenzo</title>
                <author key="mancini-marie">Marie Mancini</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcribed and translated by</resp>
                    <name xml:id="smn">Sarah M. Nelson</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Edited by</resp>
                    <name xml:id="am">Alessandro Martina</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoded by</resp>
                    <name xml:id="lrm">Liam R. Marchant</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>The Correspondence of Marie Mancini</authority>
                <publisher>University of Idaho Library</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>https://thecdil.github.io/mancini_source/</addrLine>
                </address>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Inquiry and Learning</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Room 211</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Idaho Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Moscow, ID 83844-2350</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>https://cdil.lib.uidaho.edu/</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2020</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>The Correspondence of Marie Mancini is freely distributed by the Center for Digital Inquiry and Learning at the University of Idaho Library and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-ND 4.0) United States License.
                    </p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Correspondence of Marie Mancini</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title key="1673_12_15_mm2lc" type="letter" n="45">lett 45 Marie to Lorenzo</title>
                    <author key="mancini-marie">Marie Mancini</author>
                    <persName type="addressee" key="colonna-lorenzo">Lorenzo Colonna</persName>
                    <date when="1673-12-15">December 15 1673</date>
                </bibl>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository key="colonna-archive">
                            Colonna Archive, library of the abbey of Santa Scolastica, Subiaco, Italy
                        </repository>
                        <collection>
                            Lettere di Maria Mancini
                        </collection>
                        <idno type="collection">IICP1</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents facs="DSCF8565;DSCF8566;DSCF8567">
                        <p>Document is one leaf, handwritten on recto and verso.</p>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <extent>
                                    <measure type="composition" unit="leaf" quantity="1">1 leaf</measure>
                                </extent>
                            </supportDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc hands="1">
                            <handNote xml:id="mancini-marie" medium="black">
                                Marie Mancini handwritten
                            </handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origDate when="1673-12-15">December 15 1673</origDate>
                            <origPlace>
                                <placeName key="antwerp">Antwerp</placeName>
                            </origPlace>
                        </origin>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>
                    </p>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2020-06-16" who="#lrm">
                Initial creation of XML from non-XML electronic files
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="letter" xml:id="letter_1673_12_15_mm2lc_raw" n="45" facs="DSCF8565">
                <head type="raw" xml:lang="it" />
                <note resp="#smn" xml:id="archive-note">
                Collocazione II-C.P.1. lettera 45
                Lettere di Maria Mancini – 1673
                Numero d'ordine – 27

                D. Maria Colonna-Mancini –

                =

                Lettera al Contestabile Colonna
                in data	15 Dicembre 1673 da Anversa
                Sigillo mancante – tutta di pugno –

                oggetto:
                </note>
                <pb facs="DSCF8566"/>
                <note resp="#smn">
                [[Along the bottom edge of the left side of the paper, parallel with the edge and upside down, is written the date by an archivist or a secretary. The ink looks similar to Marie's ink, but has soaked into the paper slightly differently.]]   
                </note>
                <note resp="#smn">
                [[On the right half of the sheet:]]    
                </note>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName key="antwerp">d'anvers</placeName> 
                        <date when="1673-12-15">ce 15<hi rend="sup">me</hi> dece[[mbre]] 1673</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Oliva non avendo visto letre vostre, et <hi rend="sup">percio</hi> temendo che non habiate aprovato la mia venuta s&#232; licentiato subitto ne io l'o possuto impedir di partir pero se lo potete far ritornar io naverei gusto, non avendo nessuno apresso di me, tra tanto io me <hi rend="sup">ne</hi> sto quy nella cittadella d'anvers con ordine del governatore ch'io non esca ne anche o possuto veder la citta per amor de dio, et per il bene che mi</p>
                <pb facs="DSCF8567"/>
                <note resp="#smn">
                [[On the right half of the sheet:]]    
                </note>
                <p>avete volsuto altre volte non mi fate ricever questo afronto di esser arestata piu lungo tempo ma scrivete a questo governatore che vi contentate ch io vada in brusselles in un convento ch'io vi prometto di non escirne de la mai piu sensa consenso vostro, et quando io mancassi fateme perder la vita che sara meritamente la qual cosa vi sara facile per tutto di farlo. adio non mi refusate questa ultima gratia se nolo volete far per amor mio fatelo</p>
                <note resp="#smn">
                [[On the left half of the sheet, turned 90&#xb0;:]]    
                </note>
                <p>per amor de miei figli li quali abraccio teneramente, et li mando un stuccio per uno, et uno altro per voi <hi rend="sup">et</hi> resto piu que mai vostra   </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed><persName key="mancini-marie">M. M. C.</persName></signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <note resp="#smn">
                    [[A blank space equal to about 4 lines' worth, then more writing:]]
                    </note>
                    <p>il marquese di borgomenero non vedendo vostre letre ne di don mauritio mi a lassato il piede nel fango qui [[something crossed out]] vi a da [[Marie first wrote "de" but then changed it to "de"]] pensar ci pensi. doppo essere venuta qua su la sua parola mi [[<hi rend="strike">ri</hi>]] trovo rite</p>
                    <note resp="#smn">
                    [[On the left half of the sheet, along the top edge, written upside down relative to the writing on the right half of the sheet:]]
                    </note>
                    <p>nuta sensa saper dove dar la testa; il governatore regolandosi dal primo <hi rend="sup">ordine</hi> ch' [[something crossed out]] hebbe dalla regina</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="letter" xml:id="letter_1673_12_15_mm2lc_edit" n="45" facs="DSCF8565">
                <head type="edit" xml:lang="it" />
                <pb facs="DSCF8566"/>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName key="antwerp">D'Anvers</placeName>, 
                        <date when="1673-12-15">ce 15<hi rend="sup">me</hi> d&#233;cembre <ref type="annotate" xml:id="a1673_12_15_mm2lc" n="1" style="Note that Marie's Italian is influenced by her French, and she often writes the dates of her Italian letters in French.">1673</ref></date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Oliva, non avendo visto lettere vostre, e perci&#242; temendo che non abbiate approvato la mia venuta, si &#232; licenziato subito, n&#233; io gli ho potuto impedire di partire; perci&#242;, se lo potete far ritornar io ne avrei gusto, non avendo nessuno appresso di me. Frattanto, io me ne sto qui nella cittadella di Anversa, con ordine del governatore che io non esca, neanche ho potuto veder la citt&#224;; per amor di Dio, e per il bene che mi</p>
                <pb facs="DSCF8567"/>
                <p>avete voluto altre volte, non mi fate ricevere questo affronto di essere arrestata pi&#249; lungo tempo, ma scrivete a questo governatore che vi contentate che io vada a Bruxelles in un convento, che io vi prometto di non uscirne da l&#236; mai pi&#249; senza consenso vostro; e quando io mancassi, fatemi perder la vita, che sar&#224; meritamente, la qual cosa vi sar&#224; facile dappertutto di farlo. Addio, non mi rifiutate questa ultima grazia, se non lo volete far per amor mio fatelo per amor dei miei figli, i quali abbraccio teneramente, e gli mando un astuccio per uno, e un altro per voi, e resto pi&#249; che mai vostra</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed><persName key="mancini-marie">M. M. C.</persName></signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript><p>Il marchese di Borgomanero, non vedendo vostre lettre n&#233; di don Maurizio, mi ha lasciato il piede nel fango qui, vi ha da pensare a me, ci pensi... dopo essere venuta qua sulla sua parola mi trovo ritenuta senza saper dove dar la testa; il governatore regolandosi dal primo ordine che ebbe dalla Regina.</p></postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="letter" xml:id="letter_1673_12_15_mm2lc_translation" n="45" facs="DSCF8565">
                <head type="translation" xml:lang="en" />
                <pb facs="DSCF8566"/>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName key="antwerp">Antwerp</placeName>, 
                        <date when="1673-12-15">15 December 1673</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p><persName key="oliva-gian-paolo">Oliva</persName>, having seen no letters from you, and therefore fearing that you had not approved my coming here, promptly resigned, and I was not able to keep him from leaving; so if you are able to get him to return, I would be pleased, since I have no one with me. In the meantime, I remain here in the citadel of <placeName key="antwerp">Antwerp</placeName>, under an order from the governor that I not go out; I have not even been able to see the city. For the love of God, and for the love that you</p>
                <pb facs="DSCF8567"/>
                <p>once felt for me, do not make me suffer this outrage of being arrested any longer, but write to this governor that you are satisfied that I should go to <placeName key="brussels">Brussels</placeName> to a convent, that I promise you never to go out of the convent again without your permission; and if I should ever fail to keep my word, put me to death, which will be deserved, and which action will be easy for you to carry out everywhere.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>Farewell, do not refuse me this last favor; if you do not want to do it out of love for me, do it out of love for my sons, whom I embrace tenderly, and I am sending them a case for each, and another for you, and I remain more than ever yours.</salute>
                    <signed><persName key="mancini-marie">M. M. C.</persName></signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>The <persName key="borgomanero">Marquis of Borgomanero</persName>, seeing no letters from you nor from <persName key="bologna-maurizio">Don Maurizio</persName>, <ref type="annotate" xml:id="b1673_12_15_mm2lc" n="1" style="Meaning 'he's left me hanging,' 'he's left me in the lurch.'">has left me here with my feet in the mud</ref>; he is supposed to look after me, so he should do it. After having come here on the strength of his word, I find myself stuck here, not knowing which way to turn, with the governor acting according to the first order he received from the Queen.</postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
